In the beginning, I couldn't even get
350 views on a video. Now, we're
averaging about 350 million views a
week. A lot of people think that I live
in our analytics dashboard, and I'm sure
there's a lot of marketers that they
obsess about that. But, I would say the
best retention is emotional connection.
Our community actually takes action when
they watch our videos. For a long time,
we didn't get brand deals because the
brands were not [music] thinking about
Scripted, right? They were thinking
about spectacle. But, the more important
question is, what do you want to be
known for? What do you want your brand
to be associated with? I spoke with Tim
Ellis from the NFL. My whole idea was,
huh, what if the NFL appointed a chief
kindness officer? [music]
And that turned out to be the most
successful creator activation that the
NFL has ever done, by their own words.
And if you follow these five steps,
these are the five steps that I would
say [music] are critical to making it as
a successful content creator.
>> All right, welcome to today's show.
We're here with Dhar Mann, who is one of
the biggest YouTubers on the planet, an
overall creative force. And we're
talking storytelling, we're talking
about how brands should work with
creators on today's show. Dhar, thanks
so much for joining us on Marketing
Against the Grain today.
>> Yeah, thanks. It's a true honor.
>> You've built this incredible YouTube
audience, and maybe to just give
everybody a little bit of backstory, we
have a quick video that kind of tells
you how we got here.
Yeah, evolution of Dhar. Okay, I love
Nothing like failing at a bunch of stuff
early in life, man.
>> [music]
>> I mean, that's pretty it's pretty
exciting. First of all, you have a
Samsung TV show coming. Congrats. That's
a big deal.
>> Thank you. I appreciate it. There's a
lot of people when I would say "I'm a
YouTuber in traditional film." That
would just sort of roll their eyes. And
then only when I got a deal with Samsung
and we started appearing on TV, did a
lot of folks actually take us a little
bit more serious. So, it's funny how it
works. You can have a very large
audience, very large,
you know, viewership or even studio, but
until you actually hit traditional
platforms, that's when traditional folks
start to give you a little bit of street
cred.
>> Well, and I think that's kind of what
the the opportunity is, especially for
brands or marketers. Your YouTube
audience is one of the biggest audiences
on video today. I imagine that you've
had huge brand success with your early
partners. Just walk us through like,
what does that look like?
>> Yeah, that's a great question. This all
started in my apartment
where I was just trying to talk to the
camera and help people that were going
through some kind of a hard time in
their life. The same types of hard times
that I had been through. At that time,
my format was talking directly to
camera. Nobody would watch those videos.
>> [laughter]
>> I just keep iterating, you know,
different formats. And especially
because my messaging was all about not
giving up after your dreams, not giving
up after you've been knocked down, I
couldn't give up on my, you know,
content creation process and putting out
videos. So, I kept iterating.
Eventually, I landed on storytelling and
I would just have friends and family
members be actors in videos. And when I
started that new format, that's when
things took off. So, you know, in the
beginning, I couldn't even get 350 views
on a video. Now, we're averaging about
350 million views a week.
So, just for, you know, some sort of
context, cuz when we talk about these
big numbers, you know, it's hard to
visualize. That's about three times the
Super Bowl audience every week. And
every day, we get more long-form views
than the Game of Thrones season finale.
Just to have some sort of context around
the numbers. Across all platform, Dhar
Mann Studios has 170 million followers,
but I look at it more than just audience
reach because audience to me are folks
that are watching. What I'm most
passionate about is the community that
we've built because the community are a
group that is actually emotionally
connected. And three out of four of our
community members say that they feel
compelled to take some sort of positive
action in their life after watching one
of our videos. And 89% of our audience
says that watching our videos is
actually more therapeutic to them than
talking to friends or family members or
even a therapist. Um so, you know, I'm
pretty excited about the emotional
connection that we've been able to build
with our community.
And that emotional connection now has
been able to translate to us working
with brands and helping them solve the
piece of helping to tell them their
stories, helping them build communities,
and, you know, building an audience that
really resonates with their messaging.
>> You said you were started a one format
and you iterated your way to another
format. How long did that take and what
were some of the revelations along the
way that helped you get into the winning
format?
>> Yeah, so in the beginning it was me
talking to camera. The message was like,
"Hey, what if Michael Jordan
quit playing basketball after he got cut
from his high school basketball team?"
And no one would quite watch those
videos and then my wife would tell me
like,
"Don't tell them, show them." And that
really landed on me. So, I started
storytelling instead. And I started
talking about my own experiences. Here's
what happened in my life. Here's the
lesson that I learned from it. And once
I started storytelling, my views would
still I wasn't getting a ton of views,
but I'd go from, you know, maybe 10
views to like 100 views. And then I
started trying different formats where
I'd incorporate like 2D animations in my
messaging to make it more visual. I
started adding um B-roll footage that
you can license online. And none of that
was quite again getting me like past,
you know, 1,000 views at that time. But
then I sort of had this eureka moment uh
where I was writing a script on a
napkin. I was doing a video about
infidelity. And I was talking about how
infidelity could happen with relatively
seemingly innocent acts. And the story I
was coming up with was about this
husband who was in the kitchen scrolling
Facebook. And he happened to see his
ex's post. And he was debating if he
should like it or not while his wife was
cooking him dinner in the kitchen and
had her back to him. And as I'm writing
this, I happen to look up and my
brother-in-law is visiting me. He's in
my kitchen scrolling Facebook, cuz
Facebook was the platform back then. And
and my wife's friend was in the kitchen
cooking something with her back towards
him.
So, that was my big sort of eureka
moment. I walked over to them and I
said, "Oh my gosh, would you guys be in
a video of mine?" Because keep in mind,
up until then all my content was just me
talking to camera. And they were like,
"Yeah, we'd love to be in a video, but
what do we have to do?" And I was like,
"Nothing. All you have to do is do
exactly what you're doing right now." I
[laughter] mean, in hindsight I probably
should have told him that I'm going to
portray him as a cheater.
>> [laughter]
>> I I didn't think that anyone would
actually watch those videos. Um so, you
know, I had my uh videographer start
recording. They were just standing there
doing improv. And I started narrating
the story. And that was the first time I
ever got a video to break a million
views. So, that's when I realized I
didn't even know it was called live
action filmmaking at that time because I
didn't go to film school. I never
aspired to be a filmmaker. I was just
trying to put out positive inspirational
messages to help people, but you know,
I'm very grateful that that format
caught on.
>> Well, I think one of the things that's
interesting is that you started out
doing a lot of kind of like production
kind of incremental things and it was
really like emotion and storytelling
that broke you through more than like
better camera or B-roll. And I imagine
you those things mattered once you found
the right storytelling vehicle, like
those things probably helped you
increment to better and better
performance, but I find that a lot of
people who aren't successful in the path
that you went down, they just get caught
in the loop of like I'm just going to
try to make things look better or sound
better versus like oh, I actually need
the audience to feel something very
differently. Like is that what you
discovered throughout that whole
process?
>> Yeah, absolutely. People, you're right,
Kip, they get hung up on the quality of
videos and all the what's versus the
why's. And you know, for me, a lot of
people think that I live in our
analytics dashboard and I'm looking at
all the data. I'm sure there's a lot of
marketers that they obsess about that,
but I would say the best retention that
you can have is emotional connection. If
your audience is connected to what
you're saying, they're going to stick
around. And that has been our secret for
success since day one. Kind of goes back
to how I see it that we are not just
building an audience, we're building a
community. Our community actually takes
action when they watch our videos. They
want to share our videos, they like,
they subscribe, they engage. So, like
when we work with brands, we take that
same type of psychology. We're not just
trying to read ad formats in the middle
of videos. We look at it as how do we
actually create some sort of emotional
connection between the brand and the
audience that they're trying to serve.
So, one great example is when we had the
opportunity to be the creator of the
week through YouTube's NFL partnership.
When I spoke with Tim Ellis from the
NFL, and he's like, "Gar, what is it
that you want to do?" First off, I was
like, "Wow, you're actually asking me?
You're not just
>> [laughter]
>> I was shocked.
>> Okay, he listened.
>> That's key cuz there's never any
collaboration directly between brands
and creators. It usually happens
between, you know, if a CMO makes a
directive that we need to get into
working with creators, that goes down to
their S- SVP. That goes down to, you
know, the 10 other people within the
company, right? Before then, it goes to
a brand agency, then a creator agency,
then a creator's manager, then a
creator's creative director. By the time
it gets to the actual creator, it's had
to go go through 17 different layers,
and now it's all really come down to
these four corner ad briefs that really
kill creativity. But, when we had the
opportunity to work with the NFL, Tim
was like, "Gar, what do you want to do?"
And I knew it was important to me that
the NFL was trying to show more heart
behind the sport, right? They were
having this helmets off strategy, so we
get to know the players on more of a
human level. Tim said that, "Hey, I want
the audience to know that the players on
the field are humans, the coaches are
humans, the audience members are humans.
How do we focus on that?" And so, my
whole idea was, "Huh, what if the NFL
uh appointed a chief kindness officer,
and then we went out and started doing
all these kind acts associated with
football leading up to the actual Super
Bowl?" In my mind, I'm like, "There's no
way, 2 weeks before the Super Bowl, that
the CMO of the NFL is going to approve
such an idea. Maybe if we're talking
about 2029, right? Like, this is going
to have to go through so much
bureaucracy, so much red tape." But,
Tim, you know, I'll give him so much
credit. He saw the opportunity, and
then, as soon as he realized like the
emotional connection behind it, he said
yes, and that turned out to be the most
successful creator activation that the
NFL has ever done by their own words.
So, our campaign generated Just to give
you an idea of like the type of content,
so we take like a high school football
team in an underprivileged area who
didn't have a school locker room, and we
built them an entire school locker room,
and we gave them brand new football
gear. We recorded all of this.
Um so, that video alone, you know,
probably got about 20 million views.
Then, I found out about this boy who had
lost his father. The father had a
promised the boy that I'm going to take
you to a Super Bowl game, never got the
chance to.
So, instead, we surprised the mom with
two Super Bowl tickets so she could
carry out the promise that the father
had made to the boy.
And if you saw that video, it would just
bring you to tears because you can
imagine how emotional of an experience
it was.
>> you're crying.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh it just got blurry all of a sudden.
>> Exactly.
>> So, you know, between all those
campaigns, we had over 100 million
views, over a billion impressions when
combining earned media and such. But
more importantly, we had a 94%
positive sentiment from watching our
videos, whereas the NFL historically has
been around the 65% range. And our
videos got a 10.4 brand lift through an
independent study. The highest brand
lift through any Super Bowl commercial
was 5.2, and that was the Toyota ad. So,
it was more than double the highest
performing Super Bowl commercial, and
this was all based on organic views.
So, you know, that's to the credit of
Tim and, you know, uh my team that
helped put all this together in a very
quick amount of time. But it just goes
to show that if you can move hearts,
that's how you can move communities.
>> So, you talk like a lot of what you're
talking about is how you can build an
emotional connection to an audience. And
being a kind of YouTube star or being a
creator on YouTube, you're kind of
having to think about your audience, and
you're also having to think about the
algorithm. And there are like shows on
YouTube that have done really well.
Diary of a CEO is a good example from
Steven Bartlett, where if you actually
listen to what he's done, he's just like
really analytical about the algorithm.
Like really trying to solve for every
kind of component of the algorithm. If
you actually look at his show and how
his show has evolved, it's pretty much
just structured around how the algorithm
works and what triggers the algorithm.
How do you think about that balance?
>> Yeah, so So, data to us is an amazing
feedback loop. We are an audience-first
company. And so, whereas traditional
media players, they have to create
content hoping that they're going to
find an audience after their show comes
out 18 to 24 months later. For us, we
actually have a direct relationship with
our audience. So, we're creating content
based on what our audience is asking
for. So, I'll give you one example. One
of the things that we do is actually let
our audience green-light what videos
that we create. And so, we do this
through
allowing them to
join surveys where every single week
they know that they can come to our
survey page. They get to choose titles
of the videos. They get to choose themes
of our videos. They also get to choose
plot points. Like, "Hey, here's five
different pitches. Which would you like
see happen?" When we're deciding whether
we want to build a single video into an
actual franchise, we go to our audience
first and ask them which one they
prefer. So, we build with the audience
from the start, and because we own our
distribution and data, we're able to
make decisions with them in mind
throughout the whole process.
Going back to when I started making
content, if I had But if I had
approached things from a traditional
standpoint,
I would have spent all of my money on my
very first video, it would have flopped,
and I would have been deep in debt, and
I never would have gotten off the
ground. Okay?
>> Totally.
>> It took me over 100 videos before one
went went viral. But our model works
because we spend a fraction of what
traditional media costs. So when
something didn't work, I could iterate,
I could iterate, I could keep trying.
And I think that's the reason that
production is down 35% last time I
checked within LA. Film studios are
vacant because the old model just isn't
working. And whereas the traditional
model has to go from script to screen in
18 to 24 months, sometimes multiple
years if you look at a Marvel project,
our turnaround time is 21 days. So from
the time that we actually write a script
to actually premiering on our YouTube
channel, there's only 3 weeks that has
gone by, and that's on our longest form
of content. Our shortest production
window is actually 7 days from start to
finish. And so what does that mean? We
can get feedback from our community much
faster than traditional players, and we
can iterate all along the way.
>> Is there ever a time where cuz I imagine
brands think about this when they want
to get into YouTube where
what the algorithm wants and what you
want to give your audience are in
conflict. And I'll give you like an
example. I watch YouTube for most of my
content, like um
>> Same.
>> especially for sports content, and one
of the problems with YouTube is
everything has to be so extreme, right?
And so every piece of analyst now is
like this person is slammed, this person
should be sacked, this person sucks.
There's no like in between anymore
because the has to be opposite ends of
the spectrum to like trigger the
algorithm. When you're a brand, you're
trying to figure out like how do I stand
out within this noise? And I suspect
there's times where you're like what the
algorithm wants not really where I want
to be. Do you ever feel that tension
between what the algorithm wants and
what you want to create?
>> Yeah, there's constantly that tension
and I think the difference is between
someone that creates a company versus
someone that actually builds a brand.
Like if you think about Disney, they
have brand equity. They actually stand
for something. That's a brand that
people are eager to want to take their
children or their girlfriends or wives
to to have some sort of special
experience because of the emotions that
that brand connotes. So I'll give you a
personal example. I often will now try
to incorporate AI into our various
creative processes and so when I plug
in, what are our top 100 performing
videos over the past 3 years, help me
generate new titles based on that, the
titles started going negative, right?
More clickbait, rage bait.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
>> AI is recognizing that there is an
audience interest in that. Um and so,
yeah, you know, for me, I totally
understand that we could probably get
more views if we did certain things such
as show a little bit more skin or have a
little bit more controversial titles, go
into more steamy romance. But the moment
that we did that, there's going to be
some mom out there that happens to be
walking by her child watching one of our
videos that instantly says, "You are not
allowed to watch Dhar Mann." I had to
sort of learn this by trial and error
because even when we would show like
cheat videos where somebody is cheating,
kind of going back to my original
example, I remember one of my staff
members was like, "My daughter didn't
know what cheating was until she saw one
of the videos, right?" So they had So
then I have to start thinking about
these types of things like what types of
moral values do I actually want to
convey through our videos and our
content. I think the interesting part is
there is so much negative content that
exists in the world, right? And sure,
we're all within the media space
realizing that that's the way to capture
eyeballs, but the more important
question is, what do you want to be
known for? What do you want your brand
to be associated with? For a long time,
we didn't get brand deals because the
brands that were looking to advertise
with creators on YouTube
>> [clears throat]
>> were not thinking about scripted, right?
And they were thinking about spectacle.
Because anytime you go to YouTube, if if
you're a brand allocating a budget,
you'd say put the scripted budget within
linear. And then if we go to YouTube, I
want to work with a creator that is
going to be doing some sort of big
exploding Lamborghinis or whatever it
is, right?
>> Yep.
>> Uh and I had my team come up to me, my
agency was like, "Hey, Darv, you start
creating more spectacle-based videos,
you can get a lot more brands interested
in working with you." So, 2 years ago I
had that I was at a really interesting
crossroads. I had to make a decision
which route I was going to go. I at that
time made the decision that we started
this whole studio to put out positive
content, to put out heartfelt content,
to teach positive life lessons. I'm not
going to alienate our audience and our
mission in search of views or in search
of brand deals. So, we stayed true to
our mission. And up until last year, all
of our revenue and growth has come from
platform revenue just because of how big
our audience is, and we never relied or
even received brand partnerships. But an
interesting thing has happened in the
past 12 months is that brands now are
less interested in spectacle-based
content, and they're more interested in
emotional connection with audiences. And
so suddenly, who is that player that
stayed true to that mission? It's us.
And so this year, our like within the
first quarter alone, our brand
partnerships were 10 times the amount of
the entire last year combined. And so,
it's one of those things that if you
stay true to your mission, it might seem
difficult in the beginning, and you
might be foregoing some opportunities,
but that strategy will ultimately pay
long-term dividends.
>> Don't go chasing the algorithm. Stay
true to whatever the ethos, the mission
of the storytelling you're trying to do.
And in that, you like you need to solve
for the algorithm. The algorithm is a
way to get discovered, but if you just
do solely what the algorithm wants,
you're never going to have a soul. It's
kind of what you're saying, and you're
not going to have any differentiation.
You're just going to be in the sea of
sameness with everyone else. And I think
what's interesting Dar is Kier and I
have a book coming out in the fall. It's
called Loop, Outlearn, Outmarket,
Outgrow. You can We'll drop a link in
for people watching the video. Uh and we
have a whole chapter in there about
creators. And like one of the thesis
there is you've a lot of brands out
there doing advertising, and most of
that advertising's getting ignored,
right? People are just like, "Oh, cool.
Like I'm just going to, you know, skip
your pre-roll. I'm going to do all these
things." But the creators like yourself
have all this deep resonance with their
community, right? Like they're not
You're not doing these spectacle-based
things. You're driven doing very
emotional-based storytelling. So, when a
brand partners with you, they don't just
get like awareness, they get the brand
halo effect of working with you. And
what your brand represents, what your
storytelling represents. And that to me
is what creators are all about.
>> Whether you're a consumer business, a
B2B business, doesn't matter. It's that
a creator has built this unique
reputation with their audience. And even
like you deciding with a brand and
deciding to work with a brand, you
probably, I imagine, saying like, "Hey,
does this brand represent the brand I
have built myself? And are they going to
be complimentary?" And you probably turn
down a bunch of partnerships because
they're probably not a fit for your
audience. Like maybe tell us a little
bit more about
how you work with brands, how you pick
and what brands to work with, because I
think this is so new for so many
marketers out there.
>> Yeah, really interesting question. So,
you know, going back to what I said
earlier, I'm really grateful that we
were able to build the company without
relying on brand brand deals, and that
was just by focusing on the audience
first, trust, and owning our own
distribution. But, you know, as the
landscape shifts, we're seeing declining
trust, ad fatigue, and more content
that's than ever. And so, brands, in
order to stand out in this sea of
sameness, as you mentioned, they're
looking for real engagement, not just
reach. And that's where we operate. Our
audience is emotionally invested, and
they're action-oriented,
which drives stronger performance.
So, you know, in thinking about some of
the brand activations that we did last
year, I mentioned the NFL and the Chief
Kindness Officer activation. Another
activation that we did was
when we were talking to Adobe, Adobe
said, "Dar, one of our goals is to show
that we are the official partner for
creators, and we want you to help us
tell that story." And I was like, "Oh,
that's easy, because all I have to do is
tell the truth." Because when I was
going
when I was going back to starting out,
back in my apartment, I had $600 in my
bank account, and I went to Best Buy. I
get the chills sometimes thinking about
this. I was looking at a box, it was
soft lights and a webcam, that cost
$400. That was like 2/3 of my life
savings at that time. I bought that. I
couldn't afford like real camera gear,
so I had to learn how to film everything
either on my webcam or my iPhone. And
the third thing that I did was learn
Adobe Premiere. And that's pretty much
the same journey as every creator. And
so, once I realized that, "Hey, you know
what? Adobe has been in creators'
journeys from the very inception. Now,
how do we tell that story, especially in
this world of AI and disruption, that
Adobe is still there for creators today?
That's when I came up with the idea of
creating an Adobe creator training camp.
And my thought was I will get some
OG creators, some of, you know, the the
biggest creators on the planet. I'm
going to assemble them together, and I'm
going to have them teach other aspiring
creators on how to create. And not just
by speaking on panels and giving
lectures, but by actually co-creating
with them. So, we had creators learning
from creators on how to create. And I
see that you got a video, so
>> Yeah, let's check this out.
>> billion combined followers.
>> I think that's what's so cool about
today. You get to learn from other
creators. Adobe really [music] makes the
process of creating content so much
easier, especially now that you get on
your phone.
>> I actually just shot a video with Adam.
It's such an incredible experience to be
in the same room with so many talented
content creators.
>> I've never done anything like this.
>> To hear from other types of creators
expands my inspiration and creativity.
>> We're able to create our own voice. I
taught myself how to edit.
>> collaborated with Matt and Rebecca.
We're so looking forward to working with
them.
>> I've been using Adobe for 10 years, and
what I love the most about it is I get
to use all the tools under the same
Adobe umbrella.
>> Ferman is the goat. Adobe is the goat.
It makes sense why two goats would come
together.
>> And I do think with our powers combined,
we've pulled off something that nobody
has.
>> One of the things I love about this is
it's one of the ultimate marketing cheat
codes. You bring a lot of high influence
people and let them work together,
right? Because they may get a lot of
value, they're inspired to talk about
it, they have like they want to share
each others' influence, and like this is
a great example of like Adobe was just a
benefactor. Got the whole halo effect of
this effort and if you're a marketer out
there and you're looking to do something
whether it's on a big scale, like that's
a pretty big scale having a big event,
having a bunch of people there or a much
smaller one-off scale, you get that
through that kind of shared influence
and shared alignment. But you also said
some magical things in there Dar where
it's like you came up with the idea, not
the company.
It happened all the all of these brand
partnerships seem like they happened
quickly, right? Weeks, months, not
years. And I I think that Adobe example
was was really interesting. Like what
did you learn from putting that all
together?
>> You know, it's funny is as I was after I
finished my talk doing the keynote at
the Adobe Creator Summit, I get off
stage and this lady comes me and she
goes, Dar, I want you to look at this.
This was a brief to work with the
creator that the company was signing
and there was 24 signatures required
from the brand
in order to sign this contract. And
she's like, whatever activation we were
trying to do with this creator for this
cultural moment that was happening, that
cultural moment already passed.
So, you know, there's there's so much
red tape and bureaucracy and like if you
want to work with creators, you have to
move at the speed of creators and
creativity, not at the speed that, you
know, folks are traditionally used to.
Like I have this acronym that I use and
if you follow these five steps, these
are the five steps that I would say are
critical to making it as a successful
content creator. And the acronym I use
is heart. H E A R T And so H is honor
your story. It goes back to even when I
was saying I started off in my apartment
not with the mission to actually start a
company or build a brand. I was just
trying to help people. That's my story
and that's baked into my mission.
Everyone listening to this has a story,
and that's what makes you unique. Second
is E, earn your audience's trust. Always
remember why the audience is there in
the first place, and create content that
makes them feel seen and heard.
Third is A, architect a system. The goal
isn't just to create one piece of viral
content. The goal has to be to create a
whole ecosystem that allows for a lot of
viral content. What makes Dhar Mann
Studios unique is that every single week
we put out about 5 hours of content
across 82 different channels. So, don't
just build content, build a company that
creates content. Step four is R, and
that is reach hearts. Going back to that
emotional connection. You can build a
large audience, but in order to build a
community that is actually going to take
action, you have to have them
emotionally connected to whatever you're
creating. That's going to inspire them
to share, comment, engage, and
ultimately purchase. And five, T, is
turn views into impact. And that's
always about just trying to find ways of
giving back and making the world a
better place. Because, yeah, it's great
to make money, but I think all of our
mission here on this Earth is to do
something greater than that, to give
back and help people. Kip, you mentioned
you guys have got a book coming out. I'm
sure that's all about adding value to
other aspiring marketers and companies
in the world. You're turning your views
now into impact. So, if you follow that
five-step process, H E A R T,
honor your story, earn your audience's
trust, architect a system, reach hearts,
and turn views into impact, you become a
very successful content creator or
business owner.
>> What do you think are if you apply that
to YouTube? Because I think that's one
of the predominant platforms people are
migrating to with the disruption in
search because of AI. Everyone wants to
try to figure out YouTube. It's a hard
platform platform to figure out. If you
had that framework, what are the core
beats to get right in a YouTube video
that really help you trigger both your
audience and trigger the algorithm?
>> Yeah, so even when we go back to talking
about packaging and we were talking
about clickbait and negative titles. I'm
very cognizant of the world that we live
in and so even some of our even a lot of
our videos, they appear as if it's going
to be some sort of a negative storyline.
Like for instance, on Mother's Day, we
posted a story called son ditches his
mom on Mother's Day.
That appears to be, you know, like some
sort of a negative story. But in
actuality, if you watch the story, it's
about a kid who ditches his mom on
Mother's Day, learns about the
importance and all the things that the
mom does for him, and then he decides to
come back, join her, and surprises her
on that special day. So everybody still
ends up So it's still a positive message
with the positive moral, but it could be
in packaging that helps to bring in an
audience. So I would say you always have
to start with packaging number one. Like
if we have an amazing story, but we
can't figure out what the title and the
thumbnail is going to be, then I say we
don't have an amazing story. So
packaging is your first gatekeeper.
Creators like to say that packaging is
about 80% of the success of the video.
The reason that can be somewhat of a
misleading statistic is because if
that's 80%, then what? The actual
content and the editing and the
directing the shooting and the actors
and everything the story is like 20%.
That doesn't make sense. So, what I've
come to realize is it's like you're
trying to drive to the beach and there's
different guardrails that you have to
get through every single time. And so,
80% of that effort, I would say, is in
that first guardrail, which is the
packaging. If you don't get past the
packaging, you will never make it to
guardrail two, which is the actual pitch
of the story. So, how we spend most of
our time is thinking about what the
packaging of that video is going to be.
Once you get through the packaging, then
you could start to put together what is
the what is the pitch? If I had explain
this video to you in 30 seconds, how
would I describe it? And it's just like,
you know, folks call it an elevator
pitch within business, content should
work that same way. You should be able
to explain like Kit, you did an amazing
job when we started out just saying what
the audience is going to gain from this
video. Or with Dhar Mann, we're going to
learn about creators, how brands can
work with creators, how you can optimize
your content, how you can grow your
following, right? Like you're giving the
value proposition up front and then that
also includes whatever your hook is
because you want the opening of your
video to match whatever the packaging
is. Like if I was to share my screen and
show you, you know, one of our
our last video is called five
ex-boyfriends won't let their sister
date.
And so, when you open that video, within
20 seconds, you're going to see the five
ex-boyfriends preventing the girl's love
interest from being able to date because
if you're not getting that experience
that you clicked on, then people feel
like they're going to be bamboozled and
they're going to swipe away. So,
whatever the core idea of your packaging
is, try to deliver that in the first 10
seconds, if not definitely within the
first 30 seconds.
And then from there, you know, it's what
we know. Where traditional media, I
would say starts with inception, rising
action, climax,
falling action, resolution. This is just
a classic story structure. Within
YouTube, it has to happen on a much a
faster accelerated basis.
You almost have to start with the
climax. You have very little time of
rising action. You have to get to the
climax, and then you have to keep
building from there. So, you have to be
able to tell that story much more
concisely. And you know, if you're
wondering where you're starting to lose
your audience's interest or how you can
improve your view through rate, of
course, you can just look at your
retention graphs for each video, and
that will usually give you a sign as the
areas that you're losing audience
>> the master class. Like that two-minute
clip is what anybody needs to to watch
if they're if you're creating on
YouTube. Uh last one for me, Dar, what
what's like one thing that has surprised
you
about your journey within YouTube that
works much better than you thought or is
overblown and doesn't work anywhere near
as much as you were told?
>> YouTubers can't make it more than 5
years, right? Like enjoy your five
seconds of fame kind of a thing. You
can't build a real business off of
YouTube. And I think now with the way
that
creators have evolved into real
businesses, like we don't just have
audiences, we're not just talent. We're
running real vertically integrated media
companies.
Right? We're not just distribution
anymore. We are actually creative, we're
production, and we're strategy. So,
what's amazing to me is how big of a
platform that you could build by being a
YouTuber or having any sort of really
engaged audience. YouTube is definitely
the platform where you can have the most
connected audience. Why? Because it's
long-form storytelling. Like how are you
going to be able to build a close
audience when you're doing 30-second
reels and you're just at the mercy of
the algorithm. With most of our viewers,
people are actually searching Dhar Mann,
coming to our channel. They're wanting
to see our videos versus it just being
suggested in their feed. And because
we've been able to build a real
business, you know, now whereas before
if you'd asked me 2 years ago, 95% of
our revenue was built
off of just platform revenue. That's
AdSense from YouTube and Facebook
through the ads that play in the
commercial breaks between our content.
Now, we're such a diversified business
that 20% of our revenue comes from
YouTube, 20% of our revenue comes from
Facebook, 20% of our revenue comes from
an in-house agency, and then the rest
gets spread out between FAST, our
partnership with Samsung where we reach
over 100 million households, and we were
the first creator to come to have a deal
with Samsung to do original content that
actually comes out in June. It's our
series called Unlikely Romances with
Samsung. Second is Vertical Dramas. Now
we've announced a partnership with Fox
where we're JV'ing to create 40 films
for their Vertical Drama platform called
Holy Water. Third, we are about to
announce a landmark deal with another
major studio in the ASVOD linear space.
Fourth, we also are now going into audio
with the launch of my podcast that comes
out on May 18th.
And finally is brand partnerships, which
is becoming a more meaningful part of
our business. So, look at just through a
YouTube business and community, how much
of a flywheel we were able to create to
build other businesses on top of it. So,
I'd say people probably still
underestimate, I know I did,
how big of an opportunity it is to
create an audience that's really
connected with your content and mission
on YouTube.
>> I think what's fascinating is you're
showing people, both creators who want
to build a real business, that you can
anchor that on YouTube and then really
expand. And that's kind of what you're
seeing, and you've got the podcast
coming up, you've got the new scripted
show with Samsung. But, I think the same
thing holds true for brands, that if
you're a brand, you can go and place ads
a bunch of different places, but you're
better off to work with really awesome
creators like yourself, because one, you
get your creative ideas, you get the
audience affinity, but as
the creators you partner with grow and
scale, you also then have new platforms,
new channels to work with them on, and
it's not like you're limited to, you
know, the amount of 30-second slots that
are out there. And so, I think you've
given everyone a way to rethink how they
can partner and how they can build their
own own content. And quite frankly, it's
just been a really inspiring to hear
your story, starting out from literally
like $600 in your bank account to now,
it seems like every quarter you've got
some awesome new project that's coming
out. You've been able to like scale your
impact in a really remarkable way.
Congrats on your success, Star. I really
appreciate it. And yeah, I mean, if I'm
just, for one takeaway for brands out
there, you know, you don't just need
influencers, you need a whole creator
infrastructure and creator ecosystems.
Don't think of influencers as
transactional relationships or one-off
deals, where they're just going to be
doing ad reads and interrupting the
content. Try to form direct
relationships with creators, and that
real creativity comes from those
conversations and the collaboration
between brand and influencer rather than
an ad brief.
>> I'm sure you're going to be hitting on a
lot of these things in your book.
>> Yeah, we we cover a lot of that in the
book, but there's also like that was
great party advice and to recap some of
the other advice is like trust the
creator, understand that it's a whole
different speed and process that has to
happen. Like those three pieces of
advice plus the framework, I think are
really valuable lessons for anybody out
there who's trying to work and partner
with creators to create great content.
So, Dara, thanks so much for joining us
on Marketing Against the Grain. We
appreciate it. You were up very early to
make this happen for us, so we
appreciate you. Thank you so much.
>> Thanks, guys. It was a real honor.
>> This data is wrong every freaking time.
>> Have you heard of HubSpot?
HubSpot is [music] a CRM platform where
everything is fully integrated.
>> Woah, I can see the client's whole
history, call support tickets, emails,
[music]
and here's a task from 3 days ago I
totally missed.
>> HubSpot, [music] grow better.